<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Copy of a letter from the Lords of Session to King Cha. and of King Ja. his Majesties answear to them, anent two prizes called the Palm-Tree and Patience.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Court of Session.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1371H</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077607</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2272:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Copy of a letter from the Lords of Session to King Cha. and of King Ja. his Majesties answear to them, anent two prizes called the Palm-Tree and Patience.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Court of Session.</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>James II, King of England, 1633-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinb. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>27 Jan. 1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from signature.</note>
                  <note>Title on p. [2]: Copy of His Majesties letter to the Lords of Session, anent the Palm-Tree and Patience.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Patience (Ship)</term>
               <term>Palm-Tree (Ship)</term>
               <term>Seizure of vessels and cargoes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151699:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Copy of a Letter from the Lords of Seſsion to King <hi>Cha.</hi> and of King <hi>Ja.</hi> his Majeſties An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear to them, anent two prizes called the <hi>Palm-Tree</hi> and <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your moſt Sacred Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE Received Your Majeſties Letter dated the fourth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, concerning the two <hi>Daniſh</hi> Ships called the <hi>Palm-Tree</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;</hi> which being Intimat to the Parties concerned in that Proceſs, and the Cauſe fully Debate. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Adviſing thereof, the following Doubts did ariſe; Whether or not the want of Paſſes conform to the Formula appointed by the 20 Article of Your Majeſties Treaty with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> is ſufficient alone to Confiſcate the Ships and Goods; albeit it be thereafter proved, that they belonged to the Subjects if Your Majeſties Allies. In the next place, if the Fraught-breif (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a duplicat is herewith ſent ſigned by the Clerk of that Proceſs) containing the different Ports of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> as a double Document, and ſufficient alone to Confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Ship and Goods, albeit it be thereafter proved that the Property belonged to Your Majesties Allies. And in the third place, if the ſaid Fraught-brief being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed at Sea the time of the Capture, and thereafter Exhibit to the Judge at the Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al by the Reclaimers; If that be a concealed Document and ſufficient alone to Confiſcate the Ship and Goods, albeit it be thereafter proved, they belonged to Your Majeſties Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. And conſidering that the Laws of Nations are and may be Regulat by Your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with Foreign Princes. Whereof and of Your own Inſtructioos. Your Majeſty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beſt Interpreter: We thought it our Duty humbly to offer to Your Majeſties conſideration, the Caſes abovementioned; That You may declare Your Royal Pleaſure and Opinion concerning the ſame; which in the Deciſion of this and other Proceſſes of the like Nature, ſhall be exastly obſerved. By</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Faithful, moſt Obedient, And moſt Humble Subjects and Servants.</signed>
               <dateline>Edinb. <date>27 Jan. 1684.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151699:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Copy of His Majeſties Letter To the Lords of Seſſion, anent the <hi>Palm-Tree</hi> and <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>JAMES R.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <salute>RIGHT Truſtee, and Right well Beloved Cuſins and Councellors, Right Truſtee and well Beloved Counellors, and Truſtee and well Beloved, We Greet you Well:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas by your Letter of the 28<hi>th</hi> day of <hi>January</hi> last paſt to Our moſt d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar and moſt entirely Beloved Brother lately deceaſed, you have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Queries therein contained, touching the Proceſs relating to the <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Palm-Tree,</hi> to be determined; Separatly for your greater Clearneſs, and altho We find the ſame Queries jointly Remitted to his ſaid late Majesty, in the Year 1680 and 1684, Clearly and Poſitively already Determined; Yet We being moſt deſirous to have theſe tedious and troubleſome Proceſſes put to an end, have ſeparatly Reſolved the ſame as they are now ſtated by you, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt whether or not the want of Paſſes conform to he Formula appointed by the Twentieth Article of the Treaty with the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> is ſufficient alone to Confiſcate the Ships and Goods, albeit it be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after proved that they belonged to the Subjects of Our Allies. Secondly, If the Fraught-brief according to the Duplicat ſent hither is a double Document, and ſufficient alone to Confiſcate the Ships and Goods, albeit it be thereafter proved that the Property belonged to Our Allies. And Thirdly, If the ſaid Fraught Breiff being Concealed at Sea the time of the Capture, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after Exhibited to the Judge at the Tryal by the Reclamers if that be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed Document, and ſufficient alone to Confiſcat the Ships and Goods, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it be thereafter proved that they belonged to Our Allies. As to the firſt, The want of a Paſs Conform to the Formula, is not of it ſelf a ſufficient Ground of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation, but a good Ground of Seazure, and bringing the Ship up in order to an Examination, whereupon if it be proved it belonged to an Allies, the Captor is to be allowed his Coaſts and Damages.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond, The Fraught Breiff is equal to a Double Document, becauſe it bears double Ports of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> then in open Hoſtility, and cannot be otherways underſtood, than if there were a ſeparat Fraught. Bre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ff for each of the two Ports, and is a ſufficient Ground alone to Confiſcate both Ships and Goods, according to the third Article of the Inſtructions to our Admirality, and the ſaid Letter in the year 1680, and Admits of no Probation to the Contrary. And as to the third and laſt Querie, We find the Concealing at Sea, the time of the Capture, of any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cument, is ſufficient alone to Confiſcat both Ships and Goods, and Admits of no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation thereafter to the contrary. And now upon the whole matter, We do find that the ſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Two Ships and Goods, were in Our High Court of Admiralty there, upon the foreſaid Grounds and Reaſons, Juſtly Condemned to be Good and Lawful Prizes, as wanting Paſſes conform to the Formula, and having no Paſs at all for that Voyage; as al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o having double and Concealed Documents, which jointly are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nqueſtionablie of ſuch Force by the conſtant practick of our High Court of Admirality here, the Law of Nations, and the ſaid two Letters Explanatory as ought to have Excluded all Probation to the Contrary. Therefore it is our Expreſs Will and Pleaſure, and we do hereby Ordain and Require you notwithſtanding of any former Probation to the contrary) to give your final Sentence and Determination in that Proceſs, upon the Grounds and Reaſons abovementioned, without any furder delay; And to Record theſe preſents in your Books, to be a rule for the future in the like Caſes, for both which this ſhall be your Warrand: And ſo we bid you Heartily farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at our Court at <hi>Whitehal,</hi> 
                  <date>the 28th day of <hi>February</hi> 1684, and of our Reign the firſt year.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>By His Majeſty's Command, <hi>Sic ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribitur. Drummond.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The Principle given up to Mr. <hi>Roderick M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>kein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ȝie</hi> Clerk, to lye as the Warrand for Extracting the Decreet.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
